<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<entry date="1858-19-08">
    <date>August 19</date>

    <locate1 N="New" V="Val">Newfoundland to Valentia</locate1>
    <msg1 N="New" V="Val">“See to adjustment. Can you receive President’s message? Been here since
        yesterday.” “We can’t read.” “Currents too weak to read.” “Very good currents, but can’t
        read. Send C’s.” </msg1>
    <msg2 V="Val" N="New"><locate2 V="Val" N="New">Valentia to Newfoundland</locate2> “C. C. C.
        Faster.” (This in answer to Newfoundland’s request to send C’s for adjustment.) “Send
        message fast.” (These words came in very good signals. The deflections on galvanometer very
        strong.)</msg2>

    <msg1 N="New" V="Val"><locate1 N="New" V="Val">Newfoundland to Valentia</locate1> “Have you
        received message for Mclver? Send acknowledgment.”</msg1>

    <msg2 V="Val" N="New"><locate2 V="Val" N="New">Valentia to Newfoundland</locate2> “No.”</msg2>

    <msg1 N="New" V="Val"><locate1 N="New" V="Val">Newfoundland to Valentia</locate1> “D. C. Mclver,
        Liverpool:—Arabia in collision with Europa, Cape Race, Saturday. Arabia on her way. Head
        slightly injured. Europa lost bowsprit, cutwater; stern sprung. Will remain in St. John’s,
        Newfoundland, ten days from sixteenth. Persia calls at <place>St. John’s</place> for mails
        and passengers. No loss of life or limb. CUNARD.” <loc.><date date="1958-17-08">“New York,
                August 17.”</date></loc.></msg1>

    <msg2 V="Val" N="New"><locate2 V="Val" N="New">Valentia to Newfoundland</locate2> “Cunard. All
        right. Go on.”</msg2>

    <msg1 N="New" V="Val"><locate1 N="New" V="Val">Newfoundland to Valentia</locate1>
        <msg3>THE PRESIDENT’S MESSAGE.</msg3> “Washington City. To <important><person>Her Majesty,
                Victoria, Queen of Great Britain</person></important>:—The President cordially
        reciprocates the congratulations of Her Majesty, the Queen, on the success of this great
        international enterprise, accomplished by the science, skill, and indomitable energy of the
        two countries. It is a triumph more glorious, because far more useful to mankind, than ever
        was won by conqueror on the field of battle. May the Atlantic Telegraph, under the blessings
        of Heaven, prove to be a bond of perpetual peace and friendship between the kindred nations,
        and an instrument designed by Divine Providence to diffuse religion, civilization, liberty,
        and law throughout the world. In this view will not all the nations of Christendom
        spontaneously unite in the declaration, that it shall be forever neutral, and that its
        communications shall be held sacred in passing to the place of their destination, even in
        the midst of hostilities? JAMES BUCHANAN.”</msg1>

    <msg2 V="Val" N="New"><locate2 V="Val" N="New">Valentia to Newfoundland</locate2> “President’s
        all right.”</msg2>

    <msg1 N="New" V="Val"><locate1  N="New" V="Val">Newfoundland to Valentia</locate1> “Your current
        much stronger; but cannot read your signals. Repeat.” “Received. Send a few words.” “Your
        currents very weak. Repeat.” </msg1>

    <msg2 V="Val" N="New"><locate2 V="Val" N="New">Valentia to Newfoundland</locate2> “How now,—can
        you read?”</msg2>

    <msg1  N="New" V="Val"><locate1  N="New" V="Val">Newfoundland to Valentia</locate1> “Understand.
        Better than ever. Please always commence by attack and give final signals, as we receive on
        galvanometer. Relay won’t work.” “To Whitehouse. Please send large circular
        galvanometer.”</msg1>

    <msg2 V="Val" N="New"><locate2 V="Val" N="New">Valentia to Newfoundland</locate2> “Can you take
        message for Field?” (<time time="hh 8, mm 0">At 8 P.M.</time>, Valentia had finished message
        to <person>Mr. Field</person>. Currents were strong, but very irregular, and only the last
        five words were readable. This was the message commencing “Directors have just met.”)</msg2>

    <msg1 N="New" V="Val"><locate1 N="New" V="Val">Newfoundland to Valentia</locate1> “Strength of
        your current constantly varies. Send Field’s message.” “Repeat all from beginning to
        ‘tariff.’” “You should never send more than a dozen words at a time in long messages. Repeat
        all of last message before ‘tariff.’” “Can’t read. Send dots and dashes.” “After ‘can
        you.’”</msg1>

    <msg2 V="Val" N="New"><locate2 V="Val" N="New">Valentia to Newfoundland</locate2> “How
        now?”</msg2>

    <msg1 N="New" V="Val"><locate1 N="New" V="Val">Newfoundland to Valentia</locate1> “Better.
        Repeat message to Field.”</msg1>

    <msg2 V="Val" N="New"><locate2 V="Val" N="New">Valentia to Newfoundland</locate2> “Try read on
        galvanometer.”</msg2>

    <msg1 N="New" V="Val"><locate1 N="New" V="Val">Newfoundland to Valentia</locate1> “Yes. Repeat
        Field’s message.” "All to word ‘the.’” “Understand after « met.’”</msg1>

    <extra>(The last ten messages refer to the following message to <person>Mr. Field</person>,
        which, although commenced at <time time="hh 3, mm 55">3.55 P.M.</time> on the
            <date>19th</date>, was not finished <time time="hh 1 mm 45">until 1.45 A.M.</time> of
        the <date>20th</date>.)</extra>
</entry>
